We'll definitely talk about the trade war.
肯定还是讲贸易战这事儿
But my introduction is about
但是呢我这个引子呢讲的是
You shouldn't give these NPD narcissists too much room to grow.
就是你不能给这些NPD自恋狂太多的发展空间
Because of NBT,
因为NBT啊
NPD narcissists.
NPD自恋狂啊
These narcissists
这些narcissus
Their world outlook is detached from reality.
他们的这个世界观是与现实脱离的啊
He's won so many times now
他现在win了这么多次啊
Do you know who I'm talking about
那你知道我说的是谁啊
Winning so many times is quite alarming
win了这么多次是非常可怕的
Especially when you put a few narcissists together
特别就是你把几个自恋狂加在一起
And they corroborate each other
然后互相佐证
They flatter and praise each other
互相吹马拍马屁
They chat and gossip
互相吹水
This thing is extremely dangerous.
这个东西它是是非常危险的
We already have the Sleeping Dragon.
本来就有卧龙了
And now, the Phoenix too.
还有凤雏
This is truly terrifying.
这就真的是非常可怕了啊
Well, I actually didn't want to talk about the trade war issue.
呃我其实本来不想说贸易战这方面的问题
Because I generally don't like to comment on this.
因为我一般我不太喜欢去评论这个
International current affairs and politics.
国际时事政治啊
Because it's so easy to get into arguments over this. I'm willing to focus on personal growth. But this time, I've been pushed to speak up. Because from a personal growth perspective, I'm actually willing to share. Narcissistic Personality Types (NPT) are people you shouldn't work with.
因为这个东西非常容易吵架啊 我愿意关注在个人成长方面 但是这次就是逼得我必须出来说点话了 因为我从个人成长方面 其实我也愿意说 就是这个自恋狂NPT这些人是不能与之共事的
These people often achieve great success in their careers,
这些人做事业啊通常很成功
but the main reason for their success is their capable employees.
但是事业成功的主要原因是因为他的员工给力
As long as you choose the right strategy,
你只要选择了为了正确的战略啊
even if you're sitting on assets,
甚至你躺在资产之上
it's hard to fail.
你是很难失败的啊
But let's be real
但是咱们说实在的
Sometimes being out of touch with reality can be quite problematic
有的时候你对与现实脱节就会很有问题啊
Musk's father actually has NPD
马斯克其实本身他父亲他是NPD嘛
He has some of those traits as well
他其实也有一些这方面的内容
But Musk himself is still grounded in reality
但是马斯克这个人还是与现实中他不脱节的
He's not a complete narcissist
他不是完全自恋狂
But he does have some NPD tendencies, being rather decisive
但是他有一些NPD的是一些倾向比较武断呐
How should I put it
比较怎么说
He believes his judgment is correct
相信自己的判断是正确的啊
Dong Mingzhu is also that kind of person.
董明珠也是这样的人啊
I’m not afraid of her suing me; I don’t care.
董明珠这些东西我也不怕他告我无所谓
She’s also a major narcissist.
他也是一个非常大的自恋狂
Putting her own statue in the phone, you know.
把自己的神像放到手机里边儿去哈
Right?
对不对
She doesn’t really care about the ultimate development of the company. Although she wants to improve the company’s performance, her autocratic style, her Empress Dowager-style control methods. To be honest, it's harmful to the group.
根本就不管这个集团的最终怎么发展 虽然想把集团东西发展的更好 但是他的这种独断专行 他的这种慈禧式的这种掌控方式 说实在的是对这个集团是有害的
It's harmful to this thing.
是对这个东西是有害的
Let's put Musk aside for now.
马斯克咱们按下不表
He's already considered a fairly successful investor.
他已经算是一个还是比较成功的一个投资人
And a businessman who has done well in his career.
跟一个事业上做得不错的企业家
But Trump, you can't do that.
但特朗普你不能这么干啊
Who is NAVARRO anyway?
NAVARRO是什么人啊
NAVO writes his own books.
NAVO是一个自己写书
And even fabricated a name.
还伪造了一个名字
Then he uses his own work to cite himself.
然后用来自己引证自己的
He’s an academic fraud.
他就是一个学术骗子
If you use his theories,
你用他的理论
his tariff theory,
用他那套关税理论啊
you might think it’s quite straightforward.
你就觉得这东西就能很简单了
I used to like Trump, though.
就是说我以前还是比较喜欢trump这个人的哈
Why do you like him?
为什么喜欢他
Because he’s pretty entertaining.
是因为他比较比较好玩
You know.
知道吗
It's rather simplistic
比较弱智
It's a bit more straightforward
比较简单一点
I've read his books on economics, so I know his understanding
他对经济的理解我看过他的书啊
To be frank, his grasp of economics
他对经济的理解说句不客气的话
might not even be as good as mine
可能还不如我呢啊
I've always been hesitant to comment on economic matters
我一直不愿意去评论经济上的东西
because there are plenty of experts on Bilibili in the field of economics I focus more on humanities and social sciences so I'll analyze from the perspective of history, geography, and politics Of course, there have been big names in history in politics as well and in international relations so let's talk about it we won't argue with others about it
因为在B站啊经济这方面的大咖有的是啊 我算人文社科类的东西 我就从啊史地政这方向去分析 当然历史上也有大咖 政治上面也有 国际关系上也有大咖 所以咱们来讲 咱们就不去跟别人争
these things are Trump's
这些东西是trump
if he thinks tariffs are
他如果认为关税的东西
that simple a logic
就是那么简单的那一个逻辑的话
then he raised the tariffs
然后把关税提高了
The other side would be forced to come back
对方就被迫就会回来
Manufacturing would flow back
制造业就回流了
That would be too simplistic
那他也太简单了
He didn't thoroughly study business
他没有去仔细研究商业
What is this thing?
这是什么东西啊
How can I put it?
唉怎么说呢
Let's say we're talking about a conflict
咱们就是说一个东西要打仗
To win
要赢的话
Strategies, tactics, and combat must be considered
必须战略战术跟战斗上面
That is, the strategy
也就是说strategy
Now, strategy and tactics
那strategy跟这个tactics啊
and battles
跟这个battle啊
you have to win all these campaigns
这些campaign你必须都赢才行啊
you've been winning for so long
你win跟win win了那么长时间
just having an 800,000 to 600,000 advantage isn't enough, right?
你光是80万对60万优势在我这没有用对吧
you're not a micro-management expert
你又不是微操专家
a lot at the micro level
很多在微观层面上
in real economic terms
在真正的对什么人的经济
When it plays a certain role
起了什么样的作用的时候
He is unaware of it
他是不知道的
First, let's talk about big business versus small business
首先咱们说这个big business跟small business
Their logic is different Where large enterprises truly have an impact The tariff has been raised to 104 Ours is 34 Let's first discuss where his policies have an impact
他的逻辑是不一样的 大型企业真正影响到哪 这个关税他加到104 咱们是34 咱们就先先说他的东西影响到哪
When it comes to his stuff
他的东西来讲
he adds everything together
他的东西是全部都加
we only have some specific things at home
咱们是只是在家有些具体上的东西
so on our side
所以咱们这边
the central bank's thinking is very clear
央妈这些思想是脑子是非常清晰的啊
we at least won't let a bunch of fools
咱们起码不会让一帮糊涂蛋去
control everything
就是控制这一切
you know what he adds
你知道他加的这些东西
it actually impacts American businesses, big and small
其实最影响的就是美国的这些大小企业
For large corporations,
那大的企业来讲
because their production components,
因为它的生产零部件
many critical parts need to be manufactured in China,
很多东西关键部件需要在中国生产
they only handle the assembly and manufacturing,
它只是组装制造
especially for products like iPhones and Teslas,
特别像IPHONE和特斯拉这种东西来讲
the impact is the greatest,
它的影响是最大的
if you increase it to 104%,
你加到104%来讲
it actually only affects certain components,
其实只是影响他的某些部件的东西
while some small businesses
而一些small business
Like some things in America
像在美国的一些东西
Frankly, your MAGA hats will be more expensive.
说白了你maga hat卖的就会比较贵了
You know?
你知道吗
They used to sell for two dollars.
原来可能卖两美元
Now they have to sell for four dollars.
现在就得卖四美元
Of course, these items don’t have a huge impact.
当然来讲这些东西没有是特别大的影响
But many manufacturers in the U.S. either need packaging from China, or they need specific designs and manufacturing done in China. For instance, things you think are made in the U.S. Like lawn mowers.
但是很多的美国的一些东西的制造方 他要么就是在中国需要包装袋啊 要么就是在中国需要具体的设计制造一些东西 比如一些东西你觉得是美国产的 比如说除草机
A bunch of miscellaneous items.
一种乱七八糟的东西
But in fact, the industrial models inside,
但其实里边的工业的一些模型啊
The creation of some crucial components,
一些重要的零部件的创造
American companies can't handle.
美国企业做不了
So they have to turn to China.
所以他只能找中国
And there's a significant issue with American companies,
而且美国企业有一个特别大的问题
Getting them to return to the U.S.
就是你让他回流
He can't find such skilled workers
他也没那么好的工人
He can't find such good companies
没那么好的企业
Many of those American manufacturers
很多的美国的那些制造商
Why he actually doesn't want to work with American companies
他实际上来讲他为什么不愿意找美国企业
It's not just about the price
不光是价格问题
The minimum order quantity isn't sufficient
起订量不够
They won't provide you with design drawings
人家不给你做设计图
It gets too complicated
弄得复杂了
He can't understand it, and they mess up the delivery
他看不懂还交货弄货
If they ask you for a deposit
要是跟你要定金
All sorts of messy stuff
乱七八糟的东西
He can't do a lot of things
他很多东西都做不到
China's manufacturing industry is quite comprehensive
中国的制造业呢是很完全的
So he can do a lot of things
所以他很多东西能做
You know
你知道吗
It's like playing a game
就像你玩游戏一样啊
You ask someone to craft an item for you
你找人打造一个装备
These people tell you that you need to pay
你这帮人说你得交钱
Then this one can't be made either
然后这个也打造不了
That one can't be made either
那个也打造不了
And the price is cheaper here
人家这边价格又便宜
And the shipping is fast
然后发货又快
And there are no unnecessary complications
然后又没有乱七八糟的东西
Just give me the CAD drawings So there's really no such thing as 100 percent American-made Or 100 percent Chinese-made In fact, it's made in many different places Then everyone works together This is the true purpose of economic cooperation within the WTO
你把cad图给我就行了 所以其实没有什么所谓百分之百美国制造 或者百分之百中国制造 实际上是在一些很多地方 然后大家是有所合作 这才是经济合作WTOO的真正的旨意所在
Many things are not about one-sided gains
很多东西来讲不是说光一个啊单方面的赢啊
A trade surplus means China earns money
贸易顺差就是中国挣钱
A trade deficit means the U.S. loses money
贸易逆差就是美国亏钱
It's not quite like that
不是那么回事的
It's not that simple
没有那么简单
Many industries operate together
很多行业都是在一起的
It's possible that these components are produced in China
有可能这些零件中国生产
Especially those items
尤其是那些东西
The critical design components are made in China
关键设计部分是中国生产
For many things
很多东西来讲
Some small businesses in the U.S.
美国的一些small business
It feels like it was made in America.
感觉像是在美国制造
But in reality, most of the design and manufacturing is done in China
但实际上设计制造大部分都在中国完成
It’s just branded differently in the back
它后边是贴牌
So who are you really affecting?
所以你影响的是谁啊
You’re affecting yourself
你影响的是自己的
The cost of manufacturing in the U.S.
美国制造的制造业当中的成本
There are many other things.
还有很多东西
Things that are truly 100% made in China.
真正百分之百中国制造的东西
Then there are serious items that the U.S. directly imports.
然后美国直接进口的有很严重的东西
Does it import BYD?
它进口比亚迪了吗
Does it import the Type 81 rifle?
他进口八一式步枪了吗
No.
没有啊
What does it import?
它进口的是什么
It imports groceries.
它进口的是grocery
some imported foods toys and such items he took care of those high-tech things he took care of the big river he took care of Huawei right? he took care of TikTok so he handles a lot of things like that but TikTok hasn't been completely dealt with yet
进口的一些食品 玩具这类这些东西 他那些高科技的东西他给办了呀 大江他给办了 华为他给办了呀 对不对 TIKTOK他给办了呀 所以很多东西他就是这样 但是呢TIKTOK还没有完全办
But he won’t actually have anything.
但是他不会真正有东西
If he has alternatives,
他有替代品的话
he won’t buy from China.
他就不会买中国
He won’t genuinely collaborate with China on these matters.
他真正跟中国合作这些事
Most of his business needs to work with China.
他大部分business都要跟中国合作
It’s not that the U.S. is unwilling to buy,
不是美国不愿意买
it’s just that buying from the U.S. is very expensive,
是美国买了以后非常的贵
and it’s also useless,
而且也没用
and the key is that it can’t be done right now.
而且也关键是现在做不到
So he is truly undermining the country's manufacturing sector
所以他真正是在打击本国的制造业
and the country's employment
跟本国的就业
He will continue to escalate these issues
他会把这些东西继续上升
Then the basic goods people buy will become more expensive
然后那些基础层面的买的东西会更贵
This is the impact on himself
这是他的影响自己
His 104 are his own consumers
他的104是他自己的消费者
along with these small
跟自己的这些小型的
medium, and large enterprises that are bearing the costs
中型的大型企业的这些制作方在掏
Because there's nothing that can be produced 100 percent in America.
因为没有什么东西是百分之百能在美国生产的
Let's take a simple example.
咱们就说个简单的例子
If you're a farmer in the U.S.
如果你是美国的一个农民
Would you buy American farm equipment or Chinese farm equipment?
你买美国的农机还是买中国的农机
Isn't it obvious?
这不是明摆着的事情吗
American farm equipment is so expensive.
美国的农机有多贵啊
It's way too expensive. Chinese farm equipment is much more affordable. Of course, many things are done very well in the U.S. Let's be honest. But the price is just too high. Raising it by 400% won't help. There's a tenfold difference in price.
太贵了 中国的农机有多便宜 当然来讲很多东西美国能做的非常好 咱们说实在的 但是价格实在是太贵了 你涨到400%也没用 它价格差十倍呢
Even if you raise it fourfold,
你涨到四倍
it would still be four times higher.
它也你涨到400%
It would only have quadrupled.
他也就升了四倍而已
That's still 2.5 times off.
那还差2.5倍呢
So raising the prices won't make a difference.
所以他涨这些东西没有用
Even a 1000% increase wouldn't help.
它涨到1000%也没有用
It has increased by 1000%
涨了1000%来讲
which truly affects the producers, making it even more expensive
真正影响到了他这边的这些生产商就更贵
So, what can we do about it?
所以不是那怎么着
He doesn't have the capability anymore
他没有能力了
You know that, right?
你知道吗
He doesn't have the capability
他没有能力
He's not one hundred percent sure that everything can be produced in America.
他不是百分之百都能在美国生产
Those drug-addicted folks
他那帮吸了毒的那帮
What can those lazy workers do all day?
整天好好逸恶劳的那帮工作人员能干嘛呀
He relies on Mexicans too.
他靠的也是墨西哥人啊
He’s not one of those fat Americans.
他也不是美国本本土那帮死胖子呀
Can he really count on those bucks to help him?
是不是他真能靠那帮巴克去帮他做吗
No way.
不可能的
So this is just a pipe dream.
所以这东西完全就是痴人说梦
Let’s talk about some things.
咱们有些东西来讲
We don’t import American beef.
咱们不进口美国的牛肉
We can use Argentine beef.
咱们可以用阿根廷的
We can use Brazilian beef as well.
可以用巴西的本身
People from the US, Canada, Australia, and New Zealand are all in competition.
美加澳新这些人和互相就在竞争
The US, Canada, Australia, and New Zealand are all major agricultural exporters.
美加澳新都是农业出口大国
They are also major exporters of livestock products.
都是畜牧业出口大国
We just buy from Australia.
咱们买澳大利亚的就完了
You just buy from Canada. When it comes to many of these items, And when we talk about agricultural products, Don't we produce them ourselves? It's just that, speaking of it, We need to import more things. The Import Expo also talks about this.
你买加拿大就完了 这很多东西来讲 而且咱讲农业品 咱们自己不生产吗 只不过来讲的话 咱们来讲就是需要进口更多的东西啊 进博会美也来讲
We maintain a trade balance.
咱们这保持贸易平衡
We've always played the game by the rules.
咱们一直是按规则去玩这个游戏的
So when he really imposes these tariffs,
所以他真正加这关税
He only hurts himself.
他只影响他自己
He's pushing Americans into a corner.
他这是把美国人往死路里逼了
Really.
真的啊
And his term is four years.
而且他任期4年
What are we going to do over the next three and a half years?
这接下来3年半怎么办啊
It's really scary.
真的是很可怕的
To be honest, I usually don't criticize the U.S. much.
说实在我一般我不怎么批评美国
I rarely criticize the U.S.
我很少批评美国的
Right?
对不对
Because I think both China and the U.S., as major powers, have a lot of potential.
因为我觉得中美两国大国都是比较啊有希望的
We're moving forward, forward, always progressing.
向前向前向前进的
Right?
对不对
Speaking for myself,
我本身来讲
I'm very optimistic about the various business opportunities in the U.S. in the future.
我也非常看好美国未来的商业各种机会
But you can't play the game like this.
但你不能这么玩啊
Dude, if you keep playing like this,
哥们你这样玩的话
You won't have any opportunities left.
你就没有什么机会了
If you keep this up,
你再这么玩的话
The economy will directly go into recession.
经济就直接就衰退了
So, not only is he not hurting the enemy by a thousand points,
所以而且来讲他这不是伤敌1000
He's hurting himself by eight hundred.
自损800
It's already hurting the enemy by eight hundred points,
这已经是伤敌800
And hurting himself by ten thousand.
自损1万了
That's really scary.
这就非常可怕了
Really.
真的呃
I think the U.S. is really a bit too late this time.
我觉得反正美国这下是真的是有点晚了
This trade war has already backfired on itself.
这贸易战就把自己先给打死了
There's nothing left to fight over.
这个没有什么可打的了